<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title>Hector Lopez - Hector&#x27;s blog</title>
    <subtitle>Reflections</subtitle>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://hectorlop.com/blog/atom.xml"/>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://hectorlop.com/blog/"/>
    <generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
    <updated>2024-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://hectorlop.com/blog/atom.xml</id>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Social Networks Don&#x27;t Let Us Think</title>
        <published>2024-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2024-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://hectorlop.com/blog/social-networks-dont-let-us-think/"/>
        <id>http://hectorlop.com/blog/social-networks-dont-let-us-think/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="http://hectorlop.com/blog/social-networks-dont-let-us-think/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;revelation&quot;&gt;Revelation&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#revelation&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: revelation&quot; style=&quot;visibility: hidden;&quot;&gt;#&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During my younger years, I was and avid reader of fantasy novels. However, as time passed, I gradually lost this interest. A few time ago, I decided to revisit it. Initially, I experienced a peculiar sensation within me, as if I could not focus on what I was reading. I had to reread certain paragraphs multiple times, and after approximately 15 minutes, I felt the need for a break. My body felt an unstoppable urge to grab my phone and check the notifications. A similar phenomenon occurred while I was watching a film. Initially, I was confused because, in the past, I could read for hours or watch a film without losing attention or feeling the need to check my phone. What is different now? The answer is &lt;strong&gt;social media&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That moment represented a turning point in my life. I became consciously aware of my behaviours and observed a multitude of similar behaviours, such as watching television while using my phone or using my phone while engaged in any activity requiring a degree of attention. After engaging in discussions with family and friends, I discovered that many shared a similar sentiment: our attention spans have diminished in comparison to those of just a few years ago. I conducted a review of the literature on this topic and found several studies (Das Chaudhuri &amp;amp; Imran, 2023; Shukla, 2022; Mahalingham, Howell, &amp;amp; Clarke, 2021) that supported this hypothesis. However, it is important to note that we are still in the early stages of research on this topic and that a conclusion cannot yet be emitted. Determined to address this, I limited my phone use by uninstalling apps or keeping the phone out of easy reach. Over time, I came to recognize certain situations in which I had previously been inclined to check my phone. Now that I was no longer doing so, these situations seemed peculiar, such as waiting in line, sitting on the toilet, or waiting to be attended to in a hospital. One day, while sitting on the toilet, I began to reflect on this phenomenon and I had a revelation: We reach for our phones at the slightest indication of boredom. However, these periods are the ones in which our minds are not occupied with external stimuli and we are able to spend time thinking. Consequently, if we were to substitute these moments for social media usage, when would we spend time thinking instead? The answer is both simple and alarming: &lt;strong&gt;We do not think anymore.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;consequences&quot;&gt;Consequences&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#consequences&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: consequences&quot; style=&quot;visibility: hidden;&quot;&gt;#&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon reaching this conclusion, I proceeded to consider the consequences of this phenomenon on both creativity and critical thinking. In the current world, it is evident that everyone has an opinion about everything. This is particularly evident on social media. One might inquire as to how someone can have an opinion about a certain topic if they do not spend time thinking. The answer is that we tend to copy opinions from others. It is possible that you may believe that this does not apply to you, but I challenge you to select a topic, compose your opinion about it, and then attempt to critically think about it for 30 minutes. In many cases, you will discover that you do not even agree with that argument. What I have observed is that we tend to form echo chambers and copy opinions that our subconscious mark as &amp;quot;related&amp;quot; to ours. For example, in the context of politics, individuals tend to accept the opinions of political parties or politicians that align with their own political views. However, if an opinion is presented that challenges these views, it is often rejected without considering the full range of scenarios and possibilities. If we were to dedicate more time to reflection on our beliefs, values, and the information we consume, rather than immediately accepting or rejecting it, I believe the world would be a more constructive and informed place.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other skill that is affected is creativity. It can be argued that everyone has had at least one amazing idea, whether in the shower, running, hiking, or any other activity that implies spending time alone. These activities have in common the solitude, which allows for deep thinking without distractions. Therefore, if we continue to eliminate these moments of deep thinking, we will be eliminating those moments of insight that can benefit us in every aspect of our lives.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While my observations are based on personal experience and may not be universally applicable,   I think we should be more conscious about ourselves. I recommend you, the reader, to take action on this issue and try to use your phone less and spend more time with your own thoughts. It is possible that a number of different outcomes may result from this. However, I’m confident that the overall impact will be positive. Even if we revert to our previous habits, at least we will be aware of the potential risks involved.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#references&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: references&quot; style=&quot;visibility: hidden;&quot;&gt;#&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Das Chaudhuri, U., &amp;amp; Imran, M. (2023). Influence of social networking usage on the levels of attention control and perceived memory functioning of young adults. &lt;em&gt;International Journal of Indian Psychology, 11&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, 1473-1489. &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.25215&#x2F;1103.143&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.25215&#x2F;1103.143&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shukla, A. (2022). Does social media usage influence selective attention. &lt;em&gt;International Journal of Cyber Behavior, Psychology and Learning, 12&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, 1-15. &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.4018&#x2F;IJCBPL.304905&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.4018&#x2F;IJCBPL.304905&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mahalingham, T., Howell, J., &amp;amp; Clarke, P. (2021). Attention control moderates the relationship between social media use and psychological distress. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Affective Disorders, 297&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.1016&#x2F;j.jad.2021.10.071&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.1016&#x2F;j.jad.2021.10.071&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
</feed>
